

4. MATRIX FACTORISATION
------------------------

- Collaborative filtering is a good method. Even for ... . So, why alternative approach?	
	- It is sensitive to NOISE DATA and SPARSE DATA
	- Good results only if
		- Large dataset
		- Nice and clean


MODEL BASED METHOD
------------------

- Instead of finding items or users similar to each other apply ML and DS
	- Train our Model with data
	- Predict using Model


Matrix Factorisation
---------------------
4. MATRIX FACTORISATION


Collaborative filtering is a good method. But if it is that good, why are we seeking an alternative approach?
It is sensitive to NOISE DATA and SPARSE DATA
Good results are obtained only if
 - Large data set is available
 - Data is nice and clean



MODEL BASED METHODS
Instead of finding items or users similar to each other, we apply apply Machine Leaning and Data Science in model based methods. Basic steps involved are :
Training our model with data
Predicting using model



MATRIX FACTORISATION


It has many sub categories of techniques.
CREEPY! Manages to find broader feature of users/items on their own (eg. Action or Romantic). Math doesn't know what to call newly found features which are simply described by matrices.

MAIN IDEA: 
Describe users and items as combinations of different amounts of each other.
For example, we may say Bob likes action movies as well as comedy movies. The same can told as 
Bob = 50% Action +20% Comedy
Matching movies for recommendations with these attributes is a good idea for predictions


PRINCIPAL COMPONENT ANALYSIS (PCA)
It is a statistical procedure used to reduce the features-matrix of our movies or even users. It is used as
Dimentionality reduction tool (Can't say what newly-reduced-dimensions mean)
Feature extraction tool



PCA ON USER RATINGS
- It has many sub categories of techniques
- CREEPY! Manages to find broader feature of users/items on their own (eg. Actioin or Romantic) although math
  doesn't know what to call newly found features - Just described by matrices


MAIN IDEA: Describe users and items as combinations of different amounts of each other.
		eg. Bob = 50% Action and 20% Comedy
		- Matching movies with these attributes - Good for predicting



SPARSE MATRIC ---> CHALLENGE --> PCA




Principal Component Analysis
-----------------------------

- Dimentionality reduction (Can't say what newly-reduced-dimensions mean)
- Feature extraction tool


PCA on Movie Ratings
--------------------

	PCA can boil down user-item rating matrix much smaller dimensions that best
	describes VARIANCE in data

- Often, the dimensions they find correspond to features humans have learnt to associate with items (eg. Acton-ey)
- Whatever it is about movies that causes individuals to rate them differently, PCA extracts and finds those
  'Latent Features'



[BOXES AND EXPLANATIONS]

Note: if R (Orignal Matrix) has some missing values, we can reconstruct R by filling blank values!!
      R = M Sigma(U-Transpose)	


Sigma Matrix
-------------

	Simple diagonal matrix only used to scale the values we get into proper scale

- We can multiply this sigma matrix with M or U and still R will just be product of two matrices
- Reconstruct R to get ratings of all users for all items!
- We can even predict ratings using dot products of 
		M Sigma(U-Transpose) 





SVD - Singular Value Decomposition
-----------------------------------

	A way of computing M, Sigma, U-Transpose all at once efficiently.
	Get all 3 factors in one shot!

	- Very accurate results
	- Used widely during Netflix prize competion


But wait!
	Just before applying PCA to original matrix R, how to deal with missing values?
	-You may fill missing values with averages of some sort... but there is a better way!

	Prediction: [ R(Bob, starwars) = M(Bob) . U-Transpose(Starwars) ]

	Assume we have some ratings for any given row/column in M and U-Transpose
		- We can treat this as 'minimisation of profits'
		- Find values of those complete rows and columns that best minimizes errors in known ratings R
		- Use SGD (Just one way to do it)
		- Apache Spark - different technique - ALS (Alternating Least Squares)


Note: You might be confused here because we are talking about learning the values as matrices in M and U - Actually 
      we are predicting ratings and not computing them directly which is what SVD does. We are not doing real 
      SVD Recommendations because SVD can't perform on missing data.
      Hence, it is 'SVD-Inspired-algoithm' not SVD itself. Winner of Netflix prize was a variation of SVD - SVD++


TIPS:
	- You can see source code for SVD algrithm used in surpiselib in github. But too complex to understand
	- Never write your own algorithm. Odds are too high that you will mess up somewhere. Use third party
	  library that has been used and validated by others.


Difference - SVD and SVD++
---------------------------

	- Actual loss function used during SGD
	- In SVD++ :  Merely rating item at all is an indication of some sort of interest in the item.
		      No matter what the rating was,
	- SVD++ outperformed SVD
	- Worked really well!!
	- Spooky/Creepy - Latent features -The way they work


GIVEN, THE USAGE OF SVD IN NETFLIX COMPETITION AND IT'S SUCCESS; A LOT OF RESEARCH FOCUSED ON SVD. THE BELOW
LISTED ONES ARE JUST SOME OF THE ALGORITHMS THAT WERE DEVELOPED

	- i. Factorisation Matrices
	---------------------------
		- Well suited for predicting ratings/clicks in Recommendation System
		- More 'General Purposed'
		- Handles sparse data with ease. Unlike shoehorning itself into problem like SVD
		- Available in Amazon Sage
		- Only downsize - WORKS ONLY WITH CATEGORICAL DATA
	- ii. TimeSVD++ 
	----------------
		- Predicting next item in series of events
	- iii. Factorized Personalized Markov Chains
	---------------------------------------------
		- Predicting next item in series of events
	- iv. PLSA (Promising!)
	------------------------
		- Extracts latent features from content itself
		- Use PLSA on 'movie titles' and 'description' and match them up with users
		- As they are content based, they don't do well on their own. Add it with user behaviour data




Hyperparameter Tuning - SVD
-----------------------------
	
	- Big problem in ML in general
	- A lot of algorithms are very sensitive to parameters such as Learning rates
	- They vary with datasets

In case of SVD, Hyperparameters are:

	- How many latent factors to extract?
	- How many dimensions to reduce to?

	Note: Both of them depend on the nature of data we have


Example Code
------------

[n_factors] --> SVD(Surpriselib)

.............................................................................................................
	print('Searching for best parameters')

	param_grid = { 'n_epoch' : [20, 30],		# Epochs
		       'lr_all' : [0.005, 0.01],	# Learning Rates
		       'n_factors' : [50, 100] } 	# No of Latent features to extract

	gs = GridSearchCV(SVD, param_grid, measures=['rmse','mae'], cv=3)
	gs.fit(evaluationData)

	# Best RMSE score
	print('Best RMSE score attained:', gs.best_score['rmse'])
	
	# Optimal Parameters
	params = gs.best_params['rmse']
	SVDtuned = SVD (n_epochs=params['n_epochs'],
			lr_all=params['lr_all'],
			n_factors=params['n_factors'])
............................................................................................................

	- GridSearchCV package:
		- Helps in hyperparameter tuning
		- Defines grid of different parameters you want to try different values for - Try every possible combination
		- 'param_grid' defines what to test
		- 'measures' define how to test
		- 'cv' set number of folds/cross_validation



SLIM - Sparse Linear Methods (2011)
-----------------------------------

	- Exiting results!
	- Outperformed all other recommendations (Hit Rates in TopN Recommendations)
	- Not only applicable to movies but books, music, credit cards etc. as well


MAIN IDEA: 'Sparse aggregation' of other things user has rated multiplied by 'sparse aggregation' of weights (magic!)


	Unknown score for given user for given item (entire row of stuffs user has rated)
		= [Formula]

- Because user has rated only some items and weights only exist for these items - 'sparse' aggregation  
- Extend to entire user item rating matrix: [FORMULA]


HOW 'w' IS COMPUTED?
		
		- Complicated
		- So complicated that many can't implement
		- Similar to SVD but requires higher mathematical concepts like
			- Matrix Frobenius Norm
			- L1 Norm Regularisation
		- If SLIM comes your way - Give a second look - Promising Stuff

 